Guide to the Mick Moloney Irish-American Music and Popular Culture Commercial Recordings Collection AIA.031.001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mick Moloney Irish-American Music and Popular Culture Commercial Recordings Collection
circa 1903-1999
1910-1995
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Moloney, Mick, 1944-
AIA.031.001
50.09 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 5 flat boxes, 1 oversized flat box, and 3 LP boxes
3640 sound discs
242 audiocassettes
19 item empty LP sleeves
The Mick Moloney Irish-American Music and Popular Culture Collection documents nearly a century of Irish and Irish-American music in all its permutations from Tin Pan Alley through the folk revival and beyond. The collection is comprised of 78 RPM records, 33 1/3 RPM LPs, 45 RPM records, and audio cassettes collected by Mick Moloney over the course of four decades. While the majority of the discs are commercial recordings of Irish music released on American labels, the collection also contains releases on Irish, English and Scottish labels representing both Irish music and closely related musical traditions in those countries. A small number of non-commercial acetates and privately made recordings are also found in the collection.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mick Moloney Irish American Music and Popular Culture Collection, Part II: Field Recordings. (AIA.031.002)
Mick Moloney Irish American Music and Popular Culture Collection, Part III: Mick Moloney Papers. (AIA.031.003)
Mick Moloney Irish American Music and Popular Culture Collection, Part IV: Irish Americana. (AIA.031.004)
Dorothy Hayden Cudahy Irish Memories Collection. (AIA.001)
Arrangement
The materials in this collection are organized into four series:
Series I: 78 RPM Records
Series II: 33 1/3 RPM Records
Series III: 45 RPM Records
Series IV: Cassettes
All series are arranged alphabetically by artist.
Historical/Biographical Note
Dr. Mick Moloney (1944-2022) was a native of Limerick, Ireland, and was a Global Distinguished Professor of Music and Irish Studies at New York University. He immigrated to the United States in 1973 and was based in Philadelphia until moving to New York City in 2006. A musician and folklorist, he recorded and produced over forty albums of traditional music and acted as advisor for scores of festivals and concerts, as well as being artistic director for the musical ensemble The Green Fields of America. In 1999 Mick Moloney was awarded the National Heritage Award from the National Endowment for the Arts, the highest official honor a traditional artist can receive in the United States. He was the author of the book and CD Far from the Shamrock Shore (2002), the author of numerous essays on Irish music and musical culture, and a co-editor of Close to the Floor: Irish Dance from the Boreen to Broadway (2009). Dr. Moloney received his Ph.D. in folklore and folklife from the University of Pennsylvania.
For further biographical information, see:
Steve Winnick, "From Limerick Rake to Solid Man: The Musical Life of Mick Moloney," Dirty Linen, No. 48 (October/November 1993)
1999 NEA National Heritage Fellowships online at http://www.nea.gov/honors/heritage/fellows/fellow.php?id=1999_11
Mick Moloney, Musician and Folklorist at http://www.mickmoloney.com
Custodial History
New York University's Division of Libraries, in conjunction with Glucksman Ireland House at New York University, purchased the Mick Moloney Collection for the Archives of Irish America in 2006. Until the Collection was transferred to New York University, under the supervision of Dr. Michael Nash, Head of the Tamiment Library, the materials were stored in Dr. Moloney's house in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2006.071, 2010.019, and 2010.073.
Scope and Content Note
This section of the Moloney Collection is made up of sound recordings on disc collected by Mick Moloney over the course of four decades. The majority of the recordings are commercial releases although there is small number of non-commercial acetates and privately made recordings. The collection, which began as Moloney's personal LP collection, mushroomed in 1978 when he acquired the record library of the Irish Hour, the longest running Irish radio show in Philadelphia, PA, hosted by Pat Stanton (See Patrick Stanton Papers, Balch Institute for Ethnic Studies, Philadelphia, PA.). These 542 78 RPM records inspired Moloney to seek out other early and hard-to-find Irish and Irish-related recordings. By scouring record shops, participating in record auctions and collaborating with record dealers, Moloney increased the collection over the next thirty years to its current size of 2301 78 RPM records. Over the same period, Moloney continued to acquire LPs and 45s for use as teaching resources, as a byproduct of his roles as producer and promoter, and for his own enjoyment, resulting in an eclectic mix of titles across many genres. The 718 LPs and 51 45s of particular Irish interest are included in Part II, while the remainder has been integrated into the Avery Fisher Center main collection at Bobst Library. An inventory of the original collection is available at the repository.
Taken as a whole, the discs in Part I of the Moloney collection document nearly a century of Irish and Irish-American music in all its recorded permutations from Tin Pan Alley through the folk revival and beyond. While the focus is on commercial recordings released on major and independent labels in the United States, the collection also features a sizeable number of releases on Irish, English and Scottish labels representing both Irish and closely related musical traditions in those countries. Part I is particularly noteworthy for its coverage of Irish music with broad popular appeal as compared to Part II, which is more focused on traditional instrumental Irish music.
Series I: 78 RPM Records, includes discs representing over fifty years of recorded Irish music from the early years of the format to its obsolescence in the 1950s. The vaudeville/Tin Pan Alley tradition is well represented in major label releases of Irish-themed songs performed by the first recording stars of the twentieth century such as Henry Burr, Billy Murray, Ada Jones and Nora Bayes. Sheet music for many of these titles, such as "Killarney and You," "If I Knock the 'L' Out of Kelly," and "Are You the O'Reilly?" may be found in Part IV of the Moloney collection. Humorous skits from the Irish-American stage of this period can also be found in this series such as "A Backyard Conversation between Two Jealous Irish Washwomen."
Particularly early recordings in Series I include the pre-1905 Zon-O-Phone discs, "The Mick That Threw the Brick" by Mr. John Terrell and Ed Favor's "Who Threw the Overalls in Mrs. Murphy's Chowder?" Of some interest is a mini collection of seventeen 5 1/2" Little Wonder discs from the 1910s and a sizeable number of Irish-themed Edison Diamond Discs. A quarter inch thick and requiring an alternate playback technology, Diamond Discs were produced between 1912 and 1929 when they were discontinued.
Later iterations of the Irish-American popular song tradition are abundant in Series I, exemplified by the 1930s and 1940s Decca recordings of the McNulty Family and the 1940s and 1950s recordings of Mickey and Mary Carton, Ruthie Morrissey, and Connie Foley. Examples of a parallel popular tradition in Ireland and Britain is evidenced in the many recordings of Delia Murphy for His Master's Voice, Jack Daly for Regal Zonophone and Joe Lynch for Glenside, among others.
Series I is also rich in examples of the Irish art song tradition featuring a wealth of recordings by Irish tenors such as Charles Harrison, Seamus O'Doherty, William Kennedy and John McCormack and their British counterparts Father Sydney MacEwan, Robert Wilson and Michael Duffy. Baritones, Robert Irwin and Michael O'Higgins also feature strongly while fewer examples of the trained female voice appear.
A broad sampling of Irish traditional instrumental music is also a feature of Series I. Transformations in style and performance can be readily traced from the earthy 1916 banjo and accordion duets of Edward Herborn and James Wheeler on Columbia to Sean Maguire's polished 1950s records on the London label. While original recordings by virtuoso instrumentalists Michael Coleman, Hugh Gillespie and Paddy Cronin (violin), John Kimmel and Joe Derrane (accordion) and Leo Rowsome and Tom Ennis (pipes) appear in Series I, there is also a broad array of instrumental music by lesser known traditional artists. The sound of the urban Irish-American dance halls of the 1920s and 1930s is preserved in the many recordings of Paddy Killoran's various ensembles, O'Leary's Irish Minstrels and Dan Sullivan's Shamrock Band. In addition, the Ceili Band tradition is well represented, with recordings by the Aughrim Slopes, the Austin Stack, the Ballinakill, and Frank Lee's Tara Ceilidhe Band to name a few.
While major labels, Columbia, Victor and Decca dominate the series, Bluebird, Brunswick, Okeh and Vocalion releases are also numerous, as are discs from smaller independent labels, particularly the small ethnic labels, Copley and Celtic. Foreign labels include Glenside, Irish, and Tara from Ireland and His Master's Voice, London, Regal Zonophone and Rex from England, while Scotland is represented by a host of releases on the Beltona and Parlophone labels. In fact, a distinctive feature of Series I is a strong Scottish presence. Twentieth century Philadelphia attracted immigrants mainly from the north of Ireland, particularly Donegal, a county with strong cultural ties to Scotland. As a result, the city's Irish community retained a close affinity for Scottish music. The roughly 542 78s in Series I that originated as the record library of Philadelphia's largest Irish radio show reflect this Scottish bias, with large holdings of music by such artists as Jimmy Shand and the Scots Guards Pipes and Drums.
Series II: 33 1/3 RPM Records continues to document recorded Irish music from the demise of the 78 through the ascendance of the CD in the 1990s. Some of the earliest discs in this series are 28 LPs on New York's Avoca label from the 1950s and 1960s, featuring such artists as fiddler Jackie Roche and balladeers Anne Greehy and Willy Brady.
While the popular tastes of mainstream Irish America are well evidenced in discs released on Columbia, RCA and Rego, Series II is particularly strong in documenting the renewed interest in folk and traditional music in the 1970s and 1980s. The majority of Series II consists of traditional instrumental and vocal music released on such Irish labels as Mulligan, Claddagh, Tara and Outlet and on American labels, Shanachie and Green Linnet, many of which have not to date been reissued on CD. The series also contains many Irish-language recordings on the Gael-linn label.
Contemporary folk revivals in England and America are also well represented in Series II through the releases on Topic/Free Reed and Folkways respectively, as are related vocal and instrumental traditions from Scotland, Canada, Brittany and Wales on a smaller scale. From field recordings to festival compilations to releases by major label acts, the discs in this category invariably contain at least one selection related to the Irish tradition in more or less overt ways, providing an interesting insight into the impact and evolution of Irish music and the interconnectedness of Celtic traditions on a more global scale.
Series III: 45 RPM Records achieves many of the same goals as Series II. Items of note are a multi-disc set of traditional dance music by fiddler Eugene O'Donnell and EPs by harpist/actor Christopher Casson, entertainer Pete McNulty and accordionist John Whelan.
Series IV: Cassettes includes several hundred commercially issued cassettes of Irish and Irish-American music (1980-1999), as well as some audiobooks. Artists in this series include U2, Mick Moloney, the Pogues, and more.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Record labels.; Sound recordings; Folk music.; Irish Americans -- Ethnic identity.; Radio programs.; Irish Americans -- Social life and customs.; Irish -- United States -- Songs and music.; Tenors (Singers) |z Ireland; Vaudeville.; Reavy, Ed, 1897-1988; Coleman, Michael, 1891-1945; Bayes, Nora, 1880-1928; Beades, Paddy, approximately 1913-; Kennedy, William A., 1899-; Hayward, Richard, 1892-1964; McCormack, John, 1884-1945; McNulty Family (Musical group); Maguire, Joseph; Killoran, Patrick; MacEwan, Sydney, 1908-1991; Burr, Henry, 1885-1941; Feeney, John, singer; Foley, Connie, Vocalist; Harrison, Charles, 1883-1955; Ballinakill Ceili Band; Moloney, Mick, 1944-; Murphy, Delia; Murray, Billy; Quinn, Frank, 1893-; Shand, Jimmy, 1908-2000; Stanton, Patrick, 1907-1976
- Series I: 78 RPM Records, circa 1903-1959; 2734 sound discs
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains discs representing over fifty years of recorded Irish music from the early years of the format to its obsolescence in the 1950s. Series I is also rich in examples of the Irish art song tradition featuring a wealth of recordings by Irish tenors such as Charles Harrison and John McCormack, as well as their British counterparts Father Sydney MacEwan and Michael Duffy. A broad sampling of Irish traditional instrumental music is also a feature of Series I.
  While major labels, Columbia, Victor and Decca dominate the series, Bluebird, Brunswick, Okeh and Vocalion releases are also numerous, as are discs from smaller independent labels, particularly the small ethnic labels, Copley and Celtic. Foreign labels include Glenside, Irish, and Tara from Ireland and His Master's Voice, London, Regal Zonophone and Rex from England, while Scotland is represented by a host of releases on the Beltona and Parlophone labels.
  This series contains 15 broken phonodiscs that have been stabilized by New York University's Barbara Goldsmith Preservation and Conservation Department, as well as 19 empty LP sleeves.
  - Side A: 'Ac Dhonncha, Seán, "Bríd Thomáis Mhurchadha" [OEP.1064-1] Side B: Broderick, Vincent, "Leag Uait An Scuab " [OEP.2005-1] (Gael-linn CE15) (Disk XA78 521)
  - Side A: Ackroyd, George, "Deep Blue Sea" [93556] Side B: Malin, Thomas, "Romping Bessie" [Matrix # not listed] (Pathé 20376) (Disk XA78 522)
  - Side A: Acme Male Quartet, "Mary O'Brien" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: James, Lewis, "That's How I Believe in You" [Matrix # not listed] (Pathé 20657) (Disk XA78 523)
  - Side A: Ahern, Michael, "Rose of Killarney" [110636] Side B: Ahern, Michael, "Handfull of Earth from My Mother's Grave" [110640] (Vocalion 84094), 1929 (Disk XA78 989)
  - Side A: Ahern, Michael, "Carrigdhoun" [108313] Side B: Ahern, Michael, "Low Back'd Car" [143606] (Columbia 33213-F), 1927 (Disk XA78 1252)
  - Side A: Al Goodman Orchestra and Chorus, "Irish Have a Great Day Tonight" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: Al Goodman Orchestra and Chorus, "Irish Have a Great Day Tonight" [Matrix # not listed] (Audiodisc Catalog # not listed) Non-commercial (Disk XA78 1338)
  - Side A: Albert Sandler Trio, "I'll Walk Beside You" [CA.19464] Side B: Sandler, Albert, "Lark in the Clear Air" [CA.19222] (Columbia DB 2110) (Disk XA78 347)
  - Side A: Albert Sandler Trio, Title illegible [CA.16549] Side B: Albert Sandler Trio, "Skye Boat Song" [CA.16550] (His Master's Voice I.M.448) (Disk XA78 348)
  - Side A: Alex Don Trio, "Robert Wilson Medley" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: Wilson, Robert with Charlotte, Freda and Jeannie Christie, "Cherry Rhyme" [Matrix # not listed] (Thistle T-222B) (Disk XA78 80)
  - Side A: Alexander Brothers Xylophone Band, "Nellie Kelly, I Love You" [] Side B: Alexander Brothers Xylophone Band, "Lovely Lucerne" [] (Perfect 14053-B) (Disk XA78 2304)
  - Side A: Alexander, George, "Killarney" [3235] Side B: Myers, J.W., "Where the Silv'ry Colorado Wends Its Way" [3698] (Columbia A666) (Disk XA78 2066)
  - Side A: Alexander, George, "Minstrel Boy " [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 60013) One-Sided (Disk XA78 988)
  - Side A: Alexander, George, "Oh Lord! Be Thou My Light" [1808] Side B: Burr, Henry, "Just As I Am" [3181] (Columbia A263) (Disk XA78 987)
  - Side A: Allan, Hugh, "Flow Gently, Sweet Afton" [T66278] Side B: Allan, Hugh, "There's Nobody Just Like You" [T66279] (Pathe 25005 B) (Disk XA78 2383)
  - Side A: All Star Ceilidhe Band, "Girl I Left Behind Me" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: All Star Ceilidhe Band, "Fire on the Mountain" [Matrix # not listed] (Copley 9-202) (Disk XA78 524)
  - Side A: All Star Ceilidhe Band, "Job of Journeywork" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: All Star Ceilidhe Band, "Humor of Bandon" [Matrix # not listed] (Copley 9-204) (Disk XA78 525)
  - Side A: All Star Trio, "Cuban Moon" [41248] Side B: Green Brothers' Novelty Band, "I'll Buy the Blarney Castle" [41352] (Emerson 10257) (Disk XA78 526)
  - Side A: All Star Trio, "Rose of Washington Square" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: All Star Trio, "You Ain't Heard Nothing Yet" [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 18659) (Disk XA78 538)
  - Side A: All Star Trio and Their Orchestra, "Ilo" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: All Star Trio and Their Orchestra, "Mimi" [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 18790) (Disk XA78 539)
  - Side A: Ambrose, "Did Your Mother Come From Ireland?" [TB 2610] Side B: Ambrose, "I Dream of San Marina" [TB 2637] (Decca 1164) (Disk XA78 1900)
  - Side A: American Novelty Dance Orchestra, "Down South" [] Side B: American Novelty Dance Orchestra, "Waltz Clog Medley" [] (Perfect 15816 B) (Disk XA78 2414)
  - Side A: American Quartet, "Anything is Nice If It Comes From Dixieland" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: Kaufman, Irving and Jack, "Eyes That Say 'I Love You'" [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 18589) (Disk XA78 598)
  - Side A: American Quartet, "Because You're Irish" [] Side B: American Quartet, "Oh Johnny, Oh Johnny Oh!" [] (Victor 18279-B) (Disk XA78 2458, Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Side A: American Quartet, "It's a Long, Long Way to Tipperary" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: Arthur Pryor's Band, "Soldier of the King" [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 17639) (Disk XA78 984)
  - Side A: American Quartet, "Mickey Donohue" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: Murray, Billy, "Me No Speak-a Good English" [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 19280) (Disk XA78 544)
  - Side A: American Quartet, "Moonlight Bay" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: Van Brunt, Walter J., "Harbor of Love" [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 17034) (Disk XA78 985)
  - Side A: American Quartet, "Nellie Kelly I Love You" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: Burr, Henry, "You Remind Me of My Mother" [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 18957) (Disk XA78 2068)
  - Side A: American Quartet, "She Gave Them All to Me" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: Porter and Murray, "Irish Wit" [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 16477) (Disk XA78 2067)
  - Side A: American Quartet, "When You Wore a Tulip and I Wore a Big Red Rose" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: Peerless Quartet, "Red, White and Blue" [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 17652) (Disk XA78 543)
  - Side A: American Symphony Orchestra, "Marche Hongroise" [7697] Side B: American Symphony Orchestra, "Molly on the Shore" [7672] (Edison 80628) (Disk XA78 986)
  - Side A: Ames Brothers, "I Didn't Kiss the Blarney Stone" [75687] Side B: Ames Brothers, "Clancy Lowered the Boom!" [74703] (Coral 60154) (Disk XA78 545)
  - Irish Suite Anderson, Leroy and His "Pops" Concert Orchestra Side A: "Irish Washerwoman" [83585] Side B: "Wearing of the Green" [83613] (Decca 16045) 78 Set (Disk XA78 2176)
  - Irish Suite Anderson, Leroy and His "Pops" Concert Orchestra Side A: "Last Rose of Summer" [83586] Side B: "Girl I Left Behind Me" [83584] (Decca 16046) 78 Set (Disk XA78 2177)
  - Irish Suite Anderson, Leroy and His "Pops" Concert Orchestra Side A: "Minstrel Boy" [83614] Side B: "Rakes of Mallow" [83612] (Decca 16074) 78 Set (Disk XA78 2178)
  - Side A: Andrews, James, "Killarney Waltz" [WSC.7] Side B: Andrews, James, "Medley of Scotch Reels" [WSC.10] (Regal Zonophone IZ.375) (Disk XA78 546)
  - Side A: Angus Fitchet's Scots Dance Band, "Jessie's Hornpipe" [M.3220] Side B: Angus Fitchet's Scots Dance Band, "Eight Men of Moidart" [M.32211] (Beltona BL.2604) (Disk XA78 1265)
  - Side A: Angus Fitchet's Scots Dance Band, "Circassian Circle" [M.3224] Side B: Angus Fitchet's Scots Dance Band, "Scottish Waltz" [M.3225] (Beltona BL.2606) (Disk XA78 1266)
  - Side A: Apollo Quartet of Boston, "When I Dream of Old Erin" [5296] Side B: McQuhae, Allen, "Irish Rose O' My Heart" [7646] (Edison 80621) (Disk XA78 980)
  - Side A: Archbishop O'Hara, "Archbishop O'Hara's Message on Catholic Charities Appeal – 1958 " [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 2824) One-Sided Non-commercial (Disk XA78 1666)
  - Side A: Art Hickman's Orchestra, "Avalon" [79441] Side B: Art Hickman's Orchestra, "Japanese Sandman" [79440] (Columbia A3322) (Disk XA78 2131)
  - Side A: Art Hickman's Orchestra, "Patches" [78693] Side B: Art Hickman's Orchestra, "Sweet and Low" [78664] (Columbia A2814) (Disk XA78 2129)
  - Side A: Art Hickman's Orchestra, "Whispering" [79396] Side B: Art Hickman's Orchestra, "If a Wish Could Make It So" [79398] (Columbia A3301) (Disk XA78 2130)
  - Side A: Arthur Pryor's Band, "Alpha March " [Matrix # not listed] Side B: Arthur Pryor's Band, "Birds of Love – Three-Step" [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 17193-B) (Disk XA78 2137)
  - Side A: Arthur Pryor's Band, "Irish Dances" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: Arthur Pryor's Band, "Irish Dances" [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 16368), 1909 (Disk XA78 1722)
  - Side A: Arthur Pryor's Band, "Jolly Fellow's Waltz " [Matrix # not listed] (Victrola 74121) One-Sided (Disk XA78 2155)
  - Side A: Arthur Pryor's Band, "Manisot March" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: Arthur Pryor's Band, "Kilties March" [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 18970) (Disk XA78 1723)
  - Side A: Arthur Pryor's Band, "Prince of Pilsen Selection " [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 1174) One-Sided (Disk XA78 2154)
  - Side A: Arthur Pryor's Band, "Reminiscences of Ireland – Part 1" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: Arthur Pryor's Band, "Reminiscences of Ireland – Part 2" [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 18997) (Disk XA78 1720)
  - Side A: Artist not listed, "I R A's Answer to the Black and Tans" [Matrix # not listed] Side B: Artist not listed, "Boys of '98" [Matrix # not listed] (New Republic 1109) (Disk XA78 47)
  - Side A: Artist not listed, "McGuffey's Symphony Rehearsal " [Matrix # not listed] (Presto I.R.1007) One-Sided (Disk XA78 238)
  - Side A: Artist not listed, "Irish King March " [522-1] (Silvertone 38695) One-Sided (Disk XA78 356)
  - Side A: Artist not listed, "Little Bunch of Shamrocks " [Matrix # not listed] (Victor 60025) One-Sided (Disk XA78 357)
  - Side A: Artist not listed, "Dreaming" [3701] Side B: Artist not listed, "Flannagan at the Vocal Teacher's" [3705] (Standard A477) (Disk XA78 397)
  - Side A: Artist not listed, "Where the River Shannon Flows " [Matrix # not listed] (Oxford 19872) One-Sided (Disk XA78 477)